Federico Fabio Frattini

☑: frattinf@tcd.ie☑: @FedFabFrat□: +353872172669

O: Github Page
D: Personal Website
in: Linkedin Profile

I am a PhD candidate in Economics at Trinity College Dublin, where I am working on research projects related to political economics and the economics of crime, with an applied-micro approach and a focus on causal inference. Coding enthusiast!

Education

Ph.D., Economics, Trinity College Dublin, September 2018 -(Expected) July/September 2022

Thesis title: "Essays in Political Economics"

Supervisor: Nicola Mastrorocco

M.Sc., Economics, Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, 2015-2017

Supervisor: Massimo Bordignon

B.Sc., Economics and Management, Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, 2011-2015

Supervisor: Salvatore Piccolo

Work Experience

Trinity College Dublin, September 2018 -(Expected) September 2022

- Teaching Assistant:
 - Introduction to Microeconomics (M.Sc.), Fall 2021.
 - Topics in Political Economy (M.Sc.), Fall 2019, 2020.
 - Development Economics (M.Sc.), Spring 2020.
 - Emergence of Macroeconomic Policy (M.Sc.), Spring 2020.
 - Long Run Development (M.Sc.), Fall 2019.
 - Introduction to Economic Policy A/B (B.Sc.), 2018-2019.
- Research Assistant:
 - Classifying local independent parties into a left right political spectrum.
 - Monitoring and running Python script.
 - Web scrape data on officially registered auditors (Python).
 - Read and managed dataset on Sub-Saharan African ethnicities in R.

SAS, May 2018 - August 2018

• Training Analytical Consultant: Organizing and delivering classes on SAS Base programming language.

Technologies and Languages

Software: STATA, Python, R, SQL, QGIS, SAS, Office.

Languages: Italian (native), English (fluent).

Research Projects

Setting an example: political leaders' cues and health behavior in the early stages of the COVID-19 pandemic in Mexico, with Bruno Morando and Luciano Ayala, Latin American Policy (2021)

Abstract: How do political leaders' cues affect citizen behavior regarding a new and complex issue? We address this question in the context of the early stages of the Covid-19 pandemic in Mexico, using electoral outcomes and municipal-level mobility data from Facebook's Movement Range Maps. In March 2020, Mexico's president downplayed constantly the severity of the coming health crisis by continuing his political rallies throughout the country and encouraging people to leave their homes. Using an event-study analysis, we find that, after the first press conference where his government declared mobility restrictions were not yet necessary, on March 13, citizens' geographic mobility in pro-government municipalities was higher than in cities where support for the president was less strong. Our results are robust to several specifications and definitions

of political support. Moreover, we find evidence that our results are driven by cities with higher media penetration, which implies that they can be attributed to people's reactions to the president's cues rather than to systematic differences in the preferences of his supporters.

Simultaneous elections and electoral outcomes: evidence from Italy

Abstract: This paper investigates the impact that the simultaneity of national and local elections has on the local electoral stage. Specifically, I focus on how this simultaneity impacts the local civic engagement, the political participation, the political competition and the electoral results. Methodologically, I employ a difference-in-differences design that exploits the staggered nature of the local elections in Italy, where some municipalities experience the simultaneity, while the rest do not. I find that the simultaneity affects the voters' participation positively, as well as the political participation and competition. Then, I find that the national success achieved by the right coalition spills over at the local level, both in terms of the votes share and of the ruling of the local government. Lastly, I document the existence of a split-ticket voting behaviour. Exploiting the simultaneity as a sample restriction, I find that a relevant percentage of municipalities engage in split-ticket voting behaviour on the local-national dimension. I find support for the divided government hypothesis as a possible mechanism.

Organised Crime, Public Procurement and Firms, with Decio Coviello and Nicola Mastrorocco

Abstract: What is the impact of criminal organisations on the legal economy? This paper investigates this question by studying the effect of the collusion between organised crime and local politicians in the South of Italy. In order to capture the presence of organised crime, we exploit the staggered enforcement of a national law allowing the dissolution of a municipal government upon evidence of collusion between elected officials and the mafia. We then measure the consequences of this collusion by using unique data on public procurement and firms. Difference-in-differences estimates reveal that infiltrated governments present lower average rebates and are more likely to have non-public negotiations. Results are heterogeneous across procurement macro-categories and political party colours. Moreover, firms winning a procurement contract in a captured municipality exhibit an increase in profits and labour, a reduction in capital, leaving unaffected total factor productivity.

Social capital and the power of mafia, with Francesca Calamunci

Abstract: What is the long-term effect of organized crime presence on social capital? We examine this relationship in Italian municipalities, by focusing on two scenarios. First, we focus on the historical presence of the Sicilian mafia on the island, where we employ an instrumental variable approach to address potential endogeneity concerns. Second, we focus on the Centre-North of the country, where we exploit a law ("Soggiorno obbligato") that forced organized crime members living in the South of Italy to resettle in the Centre-North area. By employing a set of variables that proxy for social capital, we find the following preliminary results. An overall negative effect of organized crime presence in the Sicilian context, in line with the idea that this presence creates an extorsive and corrupted environment which, in turn, negatively affects social capital, while a set of mixed results in the Centre-North context.

Organised crime and human capital, within-city evidence from Italy

Awards and Fellowships

Economics Department Scholarship, Trinity College Dublin, 2018-2020 2020 Government of Ireland Postgraduate Scholarship, Irish Research Council, 2020-present

Interests

Sports, with a particular interest on basketball and football. Travelling and videogames.

References

Prof. Nicola Mastrorocco (supervisor) Economics Department Trinity College Dublin n.mastrorocco@tcd.ie Prof. Gaia Narciso Economics Department Trinity College Dublin narcisog@tcd.ie

Last updated on February 20, 2022.